Soviet Union Old Believers Subject Files, Inclusive: 1952-2000, undated, Bulk: 1977-1987
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Old Believers Subject Files
Inclusive: 1952-2000, undated, Bulk: 1977-1987
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
32
The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
2 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union Old Believers Subject Files contain a variety of materials on persecution of and discrimination against Old Believers in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the beginning of the post-World War II period until approximately 2000, Keston obtained materials pertaining to persecution of Old Believers in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Persecution of Old Believers in Russia has a long history. They emerged as a group of dissenters in the 17th century schism within the Russian Orthodox Church. The Church divided over the liturgical reforms instituted by the Patriarch of Moscow Nikon in 1952-1967 and upheld by Russian Tzar Aleksei Mikhailovich Romanov. The dissenters, including both Orthodox clergy and lay people, opposed any changes to liturgical texts and church rituals. They identified themselves as “old ritualists” or “old believers” practicing traditional unchanged Orthodox faith as opposed to “new believers,” the followers of Patriarch Nikon. The official Russian Orthodox Church referred to the dissenters as “Raskolniki” (schismatics) and condemned them at the 1666-1667 Great Council.
Rejected by the official church and persecuted by civil authorities, Old Believers mostly resettled in the remote regions of northern and eastern Russia where they practiced original church rituals and opposed change, including the reforms of Tzar Peter the Great. Large Russian Old Believers communities also formed in Ukraine and Belarus as well as abroad in Turkey and Latvia. Rogozhskoe Cemetery, founded during the reign of Catherine the Great in 1771, became a spiritual and administrative center of Old Believers in Moscow.
The severe persecution Russian Old Believers experienced shortly after the 1666-1667 Great Council resulted in the elimination of the canonical clergy that supported the movement. Deprived of its hierarchy, Old Believers divided into “popovtsy” who accepted clergy defecting from the official Church, and “bespopovtsy” who let lay members assume certain clerical responsibilities. Persistent canonical and dogmatic differences within the two branches caused further division into “soglasiia” (concords). In the early 1900s, the number of concords exceeded 20.
Old Believers benefitted from the 1905 Act of Religious Toleration which granted them important political, civil, and religious rights. Between 1905 and 1917, their communities grew stronger. Unfortunately, the Old Believers status remained illegal. They could not preach or teach in public schools and faced persecution for converting new believers to the “old faith.” Under the Soviet regime, persecution included confiscation of religious property and imprisonment or murder of clergy, and many smaller concords merged or were eradicated. In 1971, the Local Council of the Russian Orthodox Church rescinded the anathemas of the 1666-1667 Great Council and recognized the validity of the old rites.
In post-Soviet Russia, Belaya Krinista Concord in Moscow became the largest and most influential Russian Old Believers community. The concord of priestly Old Believers represents the Russian Orthodox Old Believer Church. Its head, Metropolitan of Moscow and All Russia together with four local Archbishops, manage more than 200 parishes in central and eastern Russia, Ukraine, and Moldova. Other major Old Believer concords include Novozybkov beglopopovtsy, officially known as the Old Orthodox Patriarchate of Moscow and All Russia; priestless Old Believers Chasovennye; the marrying Pomortsy, officially known as the Old Orthodox Pomorian Church; the non-marrying Filippovtsy, officially Christians of Solovki and Old Pomorian Descendants; non-marrying Fedoseevtsy, officially, Old Pomorian Celibate Christian Community of Old Believers; Beguny or Stranniki, officially, True Orthodox Christians Itinerant; Spasovtsy or Netovtsy; Melkhesideki; and Edinoversty.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Old Believers Subject Files contain materials on the history, life, and persecution of Old Believers in the former Soviet Union. The materials cover a period from 1952 to 2000, with the bulk from 1977 to 1987.
The topics include but are not limited to Old Believers life in Moscow, Siberia, and Latvia; their relationship with the state and other denominations; and reports on expropriation of church property.
The files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, reports, and publications.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Old Believers Subject Files in folders, some of which were organized by categories. The original filing system has been preserved. Unsorted materials have been organized by topic and filed chronologically. The materials are in good conditions
The Soviet Union Old Believers Subject Files are arranged in one series: I. General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 32.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael., and S. B. Filatov. Sovremennai︠a︡ religioznai︠a︡ zhizn)' Rossii: opyt sistematicheskogo opisanii︠a︡. Moskva: Logos, 2003.
Robson, Roy R. Old Believers in Modern Russia. DeKalb, Ill: Northern Illinois University Press, 1995.
Kratkiĭ ocherk istorii Russkoĭ pravoslavnoĭ staroobri︠a︡dcheskoĭ t︠s︡erkvi. Moskva: [publisher not identified], 1998.
Index Terms
Subjects
Church and state -- Old Believers.; Lykov Family.; Old Believers -- Russia -- History -- 20th century.; Persecution -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Publications.; References.
- General, 1952-2000, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains bibliographic references and general information on various aspects of the life of Old Believers in the former Soviet Union.
  The series is in good condition.
  - Old Believers. General (1 of 2), 1967-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Old Believers. General (2 of 2), 1984-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Old Believers. History, 1983-1988, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individual Old Believers. Lykov Family, 1983-1986, 1989, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Old Believers. Individual Churches, 1977, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Old Believers. Church Administration. Canon Law, 1971, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Old Believers. Church. State. Law. General, 1984, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Old Believers. General, 1962-1980, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Old Believers. Church Life. General, 1975-1994, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Staroobriadcheskii Tserkovnyi Kalendar', 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Staroobriadcheskii Tserkovnyi Kalendar', 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Staroobriadcheskii Tserkovnyi Kalendar'. Copies of Selected Articles, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Staroobriadcheskii Tserkovnyi Kalendar'. Translated Articles, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Staroobriadcheskii Tserkovnyi Kalendar', 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Tserkov', No. 0, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Old Believers. Official Church Publications. Tserkov', No. 2, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Old Believers. Clergy and Priesthood. General, 1962-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Old Believers. International Contact. General, 1995, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Old Believers. Theology. Philosophy. General, 1913, 1956, 1978, 1991, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Old Believers. Unity and Schisms, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Old Believers. Statistics, 1976, 1979, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Old Believers. Peace Activities. General, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Old Believers. Church Art and Literature. General, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Old Believers. Literature. General, 1906, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Old Believers. General References, 1952-1988, 1992-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Old Believers. Article Manuscripts, 1969, 1985, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Old Believers. Publications. Bishop of Ural Arsenii, "Opravdanie staroobriadcheskoi sviatoi khristovoi tserkvi", 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)